[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want to talk about the theme of Brahma-vihāra, but starting with the Jīvaka Sutta, Majjhimikaya, 55.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, I'll just read a section, a few sections.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha says to Jīvaka, Jīvaka, I say that there are three instances in which meat should not be eaten.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it is seen, heard or suspected that the living being has been slaughtered for oneself, I say that meat should not be eaten in these three instances.
[SPEAKER_01]: I say that there are three instances in which meat may be eaten when it is not seen, not heard and not suspected that the living being has been slaughtered for oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I say that meat may be eaten in these three instances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the question is, yeah, if a person who is cultivating dharmavihāra practice, training in that practice, or developing, or developed in that practice, can he eat meat?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the answer is yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what he asked Buddha initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, that's, that's... What is the implication of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person who is cultivating things like kindness,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just a little bit aside, as a lay person, buying meat from a supermarket, you don't directly kill anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still, you go and you desire meat, you go for it, you buy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that blameless?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or blameworthy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know for sure, the animal hasn't been killed for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Probably, that meat is not sold.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be thrown away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the same amount of animals will be slaughtered.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it makes no difference otherwise, whether you buy it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, the argument is buying the meat supposes the meat industry.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's so far removed from any practical basis that it's not true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that argument is based on that assumption that we are all equal, that we are all the same, that we all make same choices, that we could all make same choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible for all humans to make same choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in theory, you can conceive it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in your mind, like, if you stop... like, even if you stop buying meat for the rest of your life, and you spend every single day of your life educating people to not buy meat, you wouldn't make a slightest dent in the meat industry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because how many billion people are there on Earth?
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to recognize that people are different.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to not eat meat or not buy meat, you cannot do it for those kind of abstract projected reasons that are not accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to find internal reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there are plenty to find for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, most of the... like, mass-produced meat is full of hormones and the way animals are killed, meat is full of adrenaline and all sorts of stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those should be your reasons if you don't want to buy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you cannot not buy it, if there is nothing else, if it's the cheapest, if you, like, need that food, then it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you say, if you need it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the... What is the...
[SPEAKER_01]: But the term is the need.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is the blameworthy?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is blameworthy there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that blameless?
[SPEAKER_01]: If we just said it's completely... What?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Buying food that you... Like, you could... you could choose chickpeas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not a moral question of blameworthy or non-blameworthy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like ethical question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's up.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can refrain from it, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you... if you... if it's too much
[SPEAKER_00]: Strain, or the other aspects of your life, you have to focus on not eating this, and you need more money, and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can't get any other form of protein, or it's too expensive, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as long as you are not supporting the killing, by ordering me to be killed, by knowing that it's being killed for you,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's so far removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, again, theoretically, you would think, yes, but we should all act from that ideal.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not if that ideal is divorced from reality, such as people are not the same, and it's impossible to make everybody to make same decisions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if for fact, there will be people they will be killing regardless, if you come across what's already killed had nothing to do with you, like, oh, well, should you feel guilty in partaking in it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can if you want to, but even so, it would be... the guilt should be based on ethical reasons, not on moral reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the suttas, I'll read further.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to suggest to me that there is a... that that would still be blameworthy to a certain degree, because of certain factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not quite sure what you're talking about now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll read further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the Buddha explains what is truly blameless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: In terms of eating meat.
[SPEAKER_01]: He continues to say, here, Jīvaka, some bhikkhu lives in dependence upon a certain village or town.
[SPEAKER_01]: He lives including one section of his experience within a benevolent mind, which he has discerned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Likewise,
[SPEAKER_01]: The second section of his experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: The third section.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fourth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, above, below, around and everywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Section or direction?
[SPEAKER_01]: Direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Section of his experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: One direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all directions of his experience, he includes within his benevolent mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: All to... as to... and to all as to himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: He lives, including the whole world, within a benevolent mind, which is abundant, exalted, immeasurable, without hostility, and without ill will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he...
[SPEAKER_01]: He practices that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: He trains that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: He lives like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's maybe someone who's already developed that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, a householder comes to him and invites him for the next day's meal.
[SPEAKER_01]: The bhikkhu accepts if he likes.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the night is ended, in the morning, he dresses and takes his bowl and outer robe, goes to the house of that householder and sits down on a seat made ready.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the householder serves him with good alms food.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does not think, that bhikkhu does not think how good that the householder serves me with the good alms food.
[SPEAKER_01]: If only a householder might serve me with such good alms food in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does not think thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: He eats the alms food without being tired to it, infatuated with it and utterly committed to it, seeing the danger in it and understanding the escape from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Jīvaka?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that bhikkhu, on such an occasion, choose for his own affliction, or for another's affliction, or for the affliction of both?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, venerable sir.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does not that bhikkhu sustain himself with blameless food on that occasion?
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what he's saying, is that that is the only blameless way of partaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it has nothing to do with meat, specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but... No, no, I'm just saying, because the first question was simply about, oh, meat, non-meat, can you eat it or not, based on what you have available.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like one topic, but now you're talking about food in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I start with that question, can a person who...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is, it's like you can abstain from eating meat all you want, you'll be equally blameworthy for eating with your desire and for wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you... and if you've done it for wrong reasons, it's impossible for you to be blameworthy, even if you buy all the meat in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I was saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I think is slightly blameworthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you, if you, if you've got a mind of desire for that meat, for that taste, not because you need it and that's the only resource you have, which can only get there, it's the cheapest thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is blameworthy in the sense of your desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's what makes it blameworthy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or killing specifically for yourself, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once that's not involved, so you know it's not killed for you, you don't suspect it's killed for you, and so on, then your desire is blameworthy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you're not talking about the meat anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're talking about food in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any food you eat with that desire, for a wrong reason, not for... not for sustenance, not out of the established mind, it will be blameworthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what I find is interesting is that, I mean,
[SPEAKER_01]: The practice of that peaceful mind, that peaceful abiding, benevolence, is not... is... how he says... one doesn't... is not tied to that food, infatuated with, utterly committed to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no desire for that thing to... that households to bring me good food, to get food.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the practice of peacefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the practice of neverliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, practice of metta, friendliness, eh, if done correctly, establishes your mind in dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there's no basis for passion, you cannot possibly exercise thoughts of, hmm, I wish he brings me this food.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just there is no passion for any food, any experience, because of the mind of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not trying to get something from anyone else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you do is protect the framework of friendliness, of benevolence, of non-harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that
[SPEAKER_00]: This implies absence of passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why those states are wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, although you're not specifically sending your metta to food, you will be unable to eat it with greed and desire, because the mind is established upon metta, properly, upon karuṇa, properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there's no basis for any passion, regardless what a passion is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the important thing there is what you said in the beginning, when you read the passage, you include experience within your mind of metta.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't beam your mind of metta towards the experience and chase it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize that this mind of friendliness, it's more general than anything, any particular person, any particular experience that can come my way, be it from north, be it from south, be it from the west, be it from the east, be it from up, be it from down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing that, you get to include all these directions within your mind of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like send your mind of friendliness down these directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you send it down north, you can't send it down east, west and south.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're trying to deal with this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about dealing with specific anger or specific issues.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about including any possibility for anger or issue within the unchanging mind of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he includes the left, he includes the right, the front, the back, up and down.
[SPEAKER_00]: He includes it all within the framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: He establishes the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Framework first, any direction second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why whatever comes to that direction, good, bad, neutral, pleasant food, unpleasant food, pleasant people, unpleasant people, will not perturb the mind, the friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's called immeasurable, not tied to any particular experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not fighting against anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's non-contention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's overcoming the fight, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not coveting the pleasure of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or trying to push away this and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, so it comes down again to feelings, that... to be able to see your feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah, because that's that's the measure of experience for everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether experience is good or bad is whether it's felt pleasantly or unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And everything's felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by discerning that the mind of friendliness can remain unchanged, regardless of the pleasant or unpleasant experience, basically, you're training your mind to remain economist regardless of how you feel, how you particularly feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, whether you're developing the principle of friendliness and metta, or principle of jhāna, the mind is developed in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this thing, being mindful of feelings, and then developing that benevolence towards feelings,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only criteria for pleasant, unpleasant, agreeable, disagreeable, it's whether how it's felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if, you know, the unpleasant person is unpleasant because you feel unpleasant on account of the experience of that person, not because that unpleasantness is contained chemically in them or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on another occasion, when your mood is good, the same unpleasant person, you don't feel unpleasant about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the unpleasantness were truly in people or things, it would always be felt the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like the same thing is sometimes felt like this, sometimes like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: That unpleasantness is basically determined how you feel at a time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you train your mind to be imperturbable in regard to how you feel at any time, there's absolutely nothing from any direction that can disturb that, because it's all second to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, the cultivation of peace, which is Brahma-vihāra, that peace is in regard to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not peace because I gain pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's peace because it's undisturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Regardless of what is happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's peace because it's undisturbed, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that cultivating one who trains in Brahma-vihāra, in the suttas,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't hear, like, he trains in Brahmavihāra and then he goes out to the village to teach, to do charitable work, to start a garden, you know, teach people how to farm, how to fish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Educate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't become a psychotherapist and deal with the traumas of people.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because that's all management.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all tying yourself down.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when he cult... he develops brahmavihāra, there's no... there's nothing about that he goes out and does outreach programs.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because that's not what brahmavihāras are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says he doesn't crave for things, he doesn't covet things, he doesn't know your will.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's your greatest contribution to the world, being incapable of your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not spreading love.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then...
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you have love without passion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you have ill-will without passion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you have ignorance, delusion, obstinacy, distraction, without passion?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you remove the passion, how can you love anyone?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you hate anyone?
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the passion is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Passion is the root of all greed, all good and all bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, because of passion, all good and bad are still tying you down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter if it's just, you know, good is better than bad, but from the ultimate point of view, if you want to be free from it all, it's equally bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you would think, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: Generosity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want to practice brahma viharas, so I must actually go out and be generous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's... there's two different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is, it is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Generosity can help, you know, sort out your circumstances, you know, people will like you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You practice generosity because it will make you feel good, which means practically you're acting out of the wanting to feel good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, some people who don't have any sense of generosity,
[SPEAKER_00]: They should, maybe, at least, do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go through the motion of generosity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to kind of... You know, in the same sense, like, if somebody is too loose, tightening up your restraint a bit more, to the point of, you know, being a bit painful, it's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if somebody is too tight, like losing their mind on account of tightness, then loosening up is good for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not always to say that loosening is always good or tightening is always good.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for somebody who is not generous, who doesn't... who doesn't, like, even have that notion, or any recognition of pleasantness of sharing, they should make the effort to develop it, by giving, literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it's important to not fall into a view that giving and generosity is somehow making you closer to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you must replace bad, which is non-giving, stealing and so on, with good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't mistake that replacing bad with good
[SPEAKER_00]: is the practice of nibbāna, because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can enable you to practice nibbāna better, but in itself it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, generosity is the...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtues be generous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not the development of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It creates a basis, but that basis in itself is insufficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a basis if there is nothing placed on that basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, there's brahma-vihāra practice and there's generosity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are two different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Two different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't practice brahma-vihāra by being generous.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can develop brahma-vihāras on account of being generous beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you can develop jhāna on account of being virtuous beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: It brings a possibility for those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue, generosity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't automatically give you insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna, parinibbāna, there we go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, brahmavihāra is the practice of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practice of dispassion, practice of
[SPEAKER_00]: Inperturbability, practice of remaining unaffected, that's why the ultimate, the highest brahmavihāra is upekha, equanimity, indifference.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you practice your friendliness rightly, you will become perfectly indifferent to everything, pain and pleasure, in yourself, let alone out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha continues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, Jivaka says, I've heard this, Venerable Sir, Brahma abides in benevolence, compassion, contentment, equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vomita, karuṇa, mudita, upeka.
[SPEAKER_01]: Venerable Sir, the Blessed One is my visible witness to that, for the Blessed One abides in those same qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the Buddha says,
[SPEAKER_01]: Jivaka, any lust, any hate, any delusion, whereby ill will, cruelty, or discontent, or aversion might arise, have been abandoned by the targeter, cut off at the root, made like a palm stump, done away with so that they are no longer subject to future arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: If what you said refer to that, then I allow it to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is... That's what Brahma has asked.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a complete dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no outreach programs, doing this, doing this, putting a smile on your face.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or spreading your love to the left and to the right and loving everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, you cannot possibly love anyone, love someone and be emotionally indifferent towards them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the cultivation of brahmavihāra is that.
[SPEAKER_00]: This passionate, emotional, imperturbability, indifference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you cannot arrive at that by spreading love.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it contradicts the very principle of that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can arrive at that by practicing non-hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's much more subtle than just visualizing love, universal love, to everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even that, whether you love somebody or not, it's determined how you feel in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you practice indifference towards your own feeling, you become indifferent, by proxy, to anyone you love or anyone you hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you overcome all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, someone might... you might not... someone might make you feel uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will not be a basis for your hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no... Somebody might make you feel comfortable, safe, agreeable, but there's no base for love and infatuation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you were saying the other day, the framework, a bit of the framework of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you said.
[SPEAKER_00]: You abide in the qualities.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you discern the quality of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes a general experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the quality of friendliness that I dwell on, you establish your mind upon that context of non-ill-will, non-harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, abiding in the quality of friendliness means developing the context of metta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can only do that on the level of your mind, not on the level of chasing down everybody you hate or don't love enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you make...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to be able to recognize those qualities?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to develop that context of non-ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, once you start developing the context of knowing, then you start to recognize that doesn't matter from which direction things come at me, they all have to converge on how I feel about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: In my mind, practice is the context of indifference or friendliness towards my own feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're friendly towards your own feeling, you will not resist it, you will not indulge it, you will not try to get rid of it, you will not try to replace it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be unmoved by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever something's contacting you, this is, yeah, peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: The common view is you practice metta towards yourself, then you spread it to others.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's true in as much you practice metta towards how you feel, in regard to anything, and then you include even experience of others within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no experience of others without you feeling something on account of experience of others.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by practicing mantra correctly, you only practice it to yourself, because it's not a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you spread it to others by basically including others within what you already cultivate towards your own feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at the expense of, okay, I finished practicing towards myself, now let me do it towards others.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's all tied to this, and then to that, and then to both, and then to neither, and then left and right, and you have no idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you develop the context correctly, context should remain unchanged, regardless whether it's you, left, right, north, east, south, doesn't matter, the framework remains of non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that framework is rooted in you being unmoved towards whatever you're currently feeling, good, bad or neutral, whichever of those things might be present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you always have the attitude of friendliness towards how you're feeling, can you experience any thirst and lust and passion?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That implies you want to change what you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're practicing indifference towards how you're feeling, can you then act out of trying to get rid of the unpleasantness that you might be feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that also implies you want to change, get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you're not friendly towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are moved by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you get moved by it by acting out of it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: You move yourself out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings cannot move you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You move yourself on account of what you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you practice metta, friendliness towards whatever currently feeling is enduring, you practice metta towards the whole world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because feelings are always convergent point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot experience the world without... unless through your own feelings in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you cover the whole world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's how you include the whole world, as you translated initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you just translate how you spread and stuff, but the same word can mean you include, you infer, you bring it in.